Guide to the Samuel Bourne photographs, circa 1861-circa 1889 RL.00130
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Photographic prints, circa 1861-circa 1889; 1; 546 prints 21 boxes
  - Madura; Palace, 1860s-1870s; 8 7/8 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN020)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 19. Title taken from print caption.
  - Madura; Palace, 1860s-1870s; 11 3/8 x 9 1/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN021)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 20. Title taken from print caption.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 8 7/8 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN022)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 21. Uncaptioned, unnumbered panoramic view, possibly the Golden Lily tank and city of Madura.
  - Madura; Nayak's Choultrie, 1860s-1870s; 9 3/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN023)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 22. Title taken from print caption; does not show up on currently known Bourne & Shepherd studio list.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 8 1/4 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN024)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 23. Uncaptioned, unnumbered (partial number appears on the album page). Exterior colonnade of a temple and small pagoda. Most likely part of the Madura (Madurai), Tamil Nadu temple complex.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/4 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN025)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 24. Uncaptioned, unnumbered (partial number appears on the album page). Interior temple columns with horses and riders. A Bourne image of a similar temple with carved pillars with horse and riders, with Mandapam and Madura in the captions, is numbered in the lower corner as 2065 (held by the National Gallery of Australia ).
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 9 3/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN026)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 25. Uncaptioned, unnumbered. Temple buildings. Most likely part of the Madura (Madurai), Tamil Nadu temple complex.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN027)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 26. Uncaptioned, unnumbered. Front view of very large temple. Most likely part of the Madurai temple complex.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/8 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN028)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 27. Uncaptioned, unnumbered. Multiple temples in the distance across a large rectangular reservoir. Madurai temple complex.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 11 1/4 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN029)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 28. View of temple front.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 8 7/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN030)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 29. Temple complex, taken from an elevated viewpoint. Most likely part of the Madurai temple complex.
  - Madura; Raft Temple, 1860s-1870s; 8 5/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN031)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 30. Title taken from handwritten caption on album page. Image shows Teppakulam tank and the Meenakshi Sundareshvara temple in Madurai; the name comes from a festival.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 11 3/8 x 9 1/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN032)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 31. View of city walls and surrounding moat or river. Seems to be Vellore Fort, Tamil Nadu.
  - Tanjore; Great Pagoda, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN033)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 32. Title taken from print caption. May be negative number 2103 on the studio list.
  - Tanjore; Temple of Subramanya, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN034)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 33. A partial number on the album page appears to be 2104, but that studio title does not seem to correspond with the title caption or image on page.
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 11 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN035)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 35. Large, high temple with small pagoda, water, and steps in foreground.
  - Trichinopoly, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN036)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 36. Title taken from album caption. May be studio print 2054, "The Rock of Trichinopoly From the East."
  - No known title, 1860s-1870s; 11 3/8 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN037)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 37. Entrance or gate to temple with small elephant sculptures at base.
  - Mahavellipore; Raths, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN038)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 39. Title taken from print caption.
  - Lucknow; General View of Chutter Munzil, 1860s-1870s; 9 3/8 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN039)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 56. Title taken from print caption. From group numbering from 1016 to 1020.
  - Simla; View of Squire's Hall and Summer Hill from the Observatory, 1860s-1870s; 9 1/2 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 11, Print RL-00130-P-UN040)
    Title assigned by dealer from unrecorded source. May be 1835 or 1836 on studio title list.
  - Meos. Mussulmans. Rajpootana, 1860s-1870s; 6 5/8 x 8 5/8 inches (Box 21, Print RL-00130-P-UN041)
    Plate number 350 in People of India (8 vols., 1868-1875), from which title is derived. Print is unmounted, undated. Probably the work of Charles Shepherd, who created many of the studio's ethnic portraits. (Source: Rayner, A Catalogue Index of Samuel Bourne's Indian Photographs)
  - Goojur Zeminders. Hindoos. Rajpootnana, 1860s-1870s; 6 1/4 x 6 1/2 inches (Box 21, Print RL-00130-P-UN042)
    Plate number 346 in People of India (8 vols., 1868-1875), from which title is derived. Comes with leaf of brief text. Print is undated. Probably the work of Charles Shepherd, who created many of the studio's ethnic portraits. (Source: Rayner, A Catalogue Index of Samuel Bourne's Indian Photographs)
  - Mewatters. Mussulmans. Originally Hindoos. Delhi, 1860s-1870s; 6 1/4 x 6 1/2 inches (Box 21, Print RL-00130-P-UN043)
    Plate number 202 in People of India (8 vols., 1868-1875), from which title is derived. Comes with leaf of brief text. Print is undated. Probably the work of Charles Shepherd, who created many of the studio's ethnic portraits. (Source: Rayner, A Catalogue Index of Samuel Bourne's Indian Photographs)
  - Weavers. Hindoos. Delhi, 1860s-1870s; 6 3/8 x 8 inches (Box 21, Print RL-00130-P-UN044)
    Plate number 191 taken from People of India (8 vols., 1868-1875), from which title is derived. Comes with leaf of explanatory text. Print is undated. Probably the work of Charles Shepherd, who created many of the studio's ethnic portraits. (Source: Rayner, A Catalogue Index of Samuel Bourne's Indian Photographs)
  - Panoramic view of Calcutta from Ochterloney Monument, 1860s-1870s; 8 1/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 21, Print RL-00130-P-UN045)
    Unmounted print. Title taken from caption written in modern hand on back of print. May be part of the group numbering 1715 to 1721 in the studio title list.
  - Chamba; Bridge on the Ravee, circa 1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-UN046)
    Title given by dealer. Likely part of the group numbering 547-549.
  - No known title, circa 1864-1865; 9 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 5, Print RL-00130-P-UN047)
    Print is unnumbered, but may be 858; part of group showing Dhal Canal in Srinuggur. Written on verso is "Lawrence Asylum, Sanawur, Girls' School," indicating a re-use of the backing material.
  - Scinde Valley Glaciers, circa 1865-1866; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-UN048)
    Unmounted print. Numbers 988 and 986 penciled on back. Dealer title given as "Cascades on the Scinde River," negative 988, but the same image in other collections (one of which has title printed on image) confirm it is either 986 or 987, Scinde Valley Glaciers.
  - Lucknow; Gateway of the Hooseinabad Bazaar, circa 1865-1866; 8 1/4 x 10 5/8 inches (Box 3, Print RL-00130-P-UN049)
    From Photograph Album 3: Western, Eastern, and South India, page 63. Title taken from print caption. Similar to studio print 1147 print held by Victoria and Albert Museum; probably 1157, with same title.
  - Dhobie's Glen. Mahabaleshwar, 1860s-1880s; 8 7/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN050)
    Image mounted on 11 x 12 1/4 inch leaf from an album. Title taken from lettered caption on image mount; "Bourne & Shepherd" written on negative. Date on back of mat, 1863, is assigned by dealer from unknown source.
  - Little Gopuram - Conjeevurum, circa 1869-1870; 8 3/8 x 11 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN051)
    Title written in manuscript hand on back of print. "Conjeevurum" is a corruption of Kanchipuram. Date assigned by library staff. Unmounted.
  - Tanjore - Gopuram From the East, circa 1869-1870; 7 1/8 x 9 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN052)
    Unsigned, unnumbered. Title assigned by dealer from unknown source; date assigned by library staff. Mounted on board.
  - Temple Tanjore in the Courtyard, circa 1869-1870; 7 1/8 x 9 1/8 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN053)
  - Kanchipuram - the Varadaraja Perumal Temple, circa 1869-1870; 7 3/4 x 10 3/8 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN054)
  - Elora - Caves and Kailasa Temple, 1870s-1880s; 6 1/8 x 7 7/8 inches (Box 25, Print RL-00130-P-UN055)
    Unsigned, unnumbered. Title assigned by dealer from unknown source; date assigned by library staff. Mounted on board. According to Bourne historian Hugh Rayner, the whole-plate size indicates that this is probably a photograph commissioned or purchased for the Frith Series of India images. May not the work of Bourne & Shepherd. Very well-preserved, with no fading present.
  - No known title, circa 1870; 8 5/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-UN56)
    Unsigned and unnumbered. Image shows the long, winding stone beam platform bridge with large pillars which crossed the wide Kaveri River in Shrirangapattna, Karnataka, near Mysore. May not be Bourne's work. Mounted on board. [Source of information and date: British Library, Crofton Collection: Topographical and architectural views in India.]